<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects | Srihari Ganesh</title><link>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/</link><atom:link href="https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Projects</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/media/icon_hu238e72ff877ecedb95a45ec9a2f2431b_15216_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Projects</title><link>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/</link></image><item><title>Stat 110 Section Notes</title><link>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/stat110/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/stat110/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Potts Mixture Models for Protein Residue Direct Coupling Analysis</title><link>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/potts/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/potts/</guid><description>&lt;p>Direct coupling analysis (DCA) is used to identify coevolving protein residues and understand structural and functional constraints in proteins. In such methods, Potts models parametrize the proteins and using a multiple sequence alignment (MSA); these sequences are assumed to come from a single underlying Potts model. However, MSAs can contain heterogeneity: for example, &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-05750-0" type="link" id="Harvard">in an MSA of the murA-lpxC system, only a subset of the seqeunces interact&lt;/a>. As an undergraduate researcher in the &lt;a href="https://www.deboramarkslab.com/" id="Harvard" type="link">&lt;b>Marks Lab&lt;/b>&lt;/a> at Harvard Medical School, I implemented a mixture model with the EVcouplings pipeline using an expectation-maximization algorithm to simultaneously infer class assignments of each sequence in an MSA and the Potts model parameters of each class. However, the algorithm failed to infer clusters correlated with interaction. This work was supported by the Harvard College Research Program (HCRP).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Real-Time Dynamic Programming for *De Novo* Genome Assembly</title><link>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/stat234/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/stat234/</guid><description>&lt;p>The DNA fragment assembly problem is an important and active field of research with applications in every field of biology. Exploratory work has previously been done to attempt to apply reinforcement learning to fragment assembly - namely, Q-learning was used on an episodic Markov Decision Process (MDP) model of the problem. For my final project in &lt;a href="http://people.seas.harvard.edu/~samurphy/teaching/stat234spring2022/syllabus.htm" id="Harvard" type="link">&lt;b>Stat 234&lt;/b>&lt;/a> (a graduate reinforcement learning seminar taught by &lt;a href="http://people.seas.harvard.edu/~samurphy/" id="Harvard" type="link">&lt;b>Professor Susan Murphy&lt;/b>&lt;/a>), I implemented Real-Time Dynamic Programming (RTDP), a learning algorithm that is more suited for searching sparse MDPs, and found improved performance over Q-learning in simulations on sythetic microgenomes. However, issues with memory requirements and the lack of flexibility when using an MDP formulation re-establish that such approaches are likely infeasible at scale.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Modeling Evolutionary Dynamics of *E. coli* in the Long-Term Stationary Phase</title><link>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/ltsp/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/ltsp/</guid><description>&lt;p>Bacteria can maintain a near-constant population size for years without an external food source in a state known as the long-term stationary phase (LTSP). However, they do not hibernate - instead, they survive by recycling the nutrients of dead bacteria, creating a dynamic and evolving environment. In the &lt;a href="https://cluzel.fas.harvard.edu/" id="Harvard" type="link">&lt;b>Cluzel Lab&lt;/b>&lt;/a> at Harvard, we experimentally introduced an evolutionary pressure in &lt;em> E. coli&lt;/em> by transforming a plasmid with overexpressed nonessential proteins, including YFP, into the bacteria to increase their protein burden, and followed the state of the plasmid using the fluorescent reporter. We also developed a system of differential equations to model the system: the introduction of oscillating protein burdens led to coexistence between proteins of different average burdens, which could allow us to better explain past experimental observations. This work was supported by the Program for Research in Science and Engineering (PRISE) at Harvard College.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A Local Existence and Uniqueness Theorem for First Order Differential Equations</title><link>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/math22b/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/math22b/</guid><description>&lt;p>As a student in Math 22b, taught by &lt;a href="https://www.math.harvard.edu/people/grundmeier-dusty/" id="Harvard" type="link">&lt;b>Dr. Dusty Grundmeier&lt;/b>&lt;/a>, I learned introductory proof-based vector calculus with some exposure to limits and continuity. However, I was interested in getting more exposure to real analysis, so for my final project I learned about existence and uniqueness theorems for differential equations and wrote an expository paper presenting a simple case of such a theorem.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>