<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>laboratory | Srihari Ganesh</title><link>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/tag/laboratory/</link><atom:link href="https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/tag/laboratory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>laboratory</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/media/icon_hu238e72ff877ecedb95a45ec9a2f2431b_15216_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>laboratory</title><link>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/tag/laboratory/</link></image><item><title>Potts Mixture Models for Protein Residue Direct Coupling Analysis</title><link>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/potts/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/potts/</guid><description>&lt;p>Direct coupling analysis (DCA) is used to identify coevolving protein residues and understand structural and functional constraints in proteins. In such methods, Potts models parametrize the proteins and using a multiple sequence alignment (MSA); these sequences are assumed to come from a single underlying Potts model. However, MSAs can contain heterogeneity: for example, &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-05750-0" type="link" id="Harvard">in an MSA of the murA-lpxC system, only a subset of the seqeunces interact&lt;/a>. As an undergraduate researcher in the &lt;a href="https://www.deboramarkslab.com/" id="Harvard" type="link">&lt;b>Marks Lab&lt;/b>&lt;/a> at Harvard Medical School, I implemented a mixture model with the EVcouplings pipeline using an expectation-maximization algorithm to simultaneously infer class assignments of each sequence in an MSA and the Potts model parameters of each class. However, the algorithm failed to infer clusters correlated with interaction. This work was supported by the Harvard College Research Program (HCRP).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Modeling Evolutionary Dynamics of *E. coli* in the Long-Term Stationary Phase</title><link>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/ltsp/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://srihari-ganesh.github.io/projects/ltsp/</guid><description>&lt;p>Bacteria can maintain a near-constant population size for years without an external food source in a state known as the long-term stationary phase (LTSP). However, they do not hibernate - instead, they survive by recycling the nutrients of dead bacteria, creating a dynamic and evolving environment. In the &lt;a href="https://cluzel.fas.harvard.edu/" id="Harvard" type="link">&lt;b>Cluzel Lab&lt;/b>&lt;/a> at Harvard, we experimentally introduced an evolutionary pressure in &lt;em> E. coli&lt;/em> by transforming a plasmid with overexpressed nonessential proteins, including YFP, into the bacteria to increase their protein burden, and followed the state of the plasmid using the fluorescent reporter. We also developed a system of differential equations to model the system: the introduction of oscillating protein burdens led to coexistence between proteins of different average burdens, which could allow us to better explain past experimental observations. This work was supported by the Program for Research in Science and Engineering (PRISE) at Harvard College.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>